Guide to the William Hillman Shockley Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
William Hillman Shockley papers
circa 1860-1971
1890-1920
SC1108
Shockley, William Hillman, 1855-1925.
2.25 Linear feet (5 boxes)
The materials consist of photographs, lecture notes, letters, books, and manuscripts documenting Shockley’s career as a mining engineer and professor at Stanford, including documentation of geology expeditions to Alaska, China and Russia.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Associated Materials
William Hillman Shockley Collection (University of Nevada, Las Vegas, Department of Special Collections)
William Hillman Shockley Photographs (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University)
Biograhpical/Historical note
William Hillman Shockley (1855-1925) was an American mining engineer and amateur photographer. He worked and traveled in Russia, Korea, Australia, and China, and was active in the Chinese mining regions during the same approximate period when another American, Herbert Hoover, also worked as a young mining engineer. Shockley was the father of William B. Shockley, inventor of the transistor and winner of the Nobel Prize for Physics (1956). He married May Bradford, who had been a federal deputy surveyor of the mineral lands. The Shockley's son William B. was born in England in 1910; they returned to the U.S. in 1913.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of photographs, lecture notes, letters, books, and manuscripts documenting Shockley’s career as a mining engineer and professor at Stanford, including documentation of geology expeditions to Alaska, China and Russia.
Access Terms
Shockley, William Hillman, 1855-1925.; China--Pictorial works.; Coal mines and mining--China.; Coal mines and mining--Russia.; Documentary photography--China.; Documentary photography--Russia.; Mining engineering--Pictorial works.; Mining geology.; Photoprints.; Russia--Pictorial works
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Biographical/Genealogical (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Birth certificate - William Bradford Shockley (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bookplates - William H. Shockley (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chinese booklet (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clipping from The Nevadan, 1971 Jul 11 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Clipping re William I. Shockley, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - evelopes (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and photos, 1888-1915 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1924 Nov 18-Dec 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence - laid in In Search of a Siberian Klondike (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Reprints and notes - laid in Russian Notes journal (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Colorado Meeting of the American Institute of Mining Engineers, 1918 Sep 1-6 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Mining Engineers related (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Bank book, circa 1890s (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Book cover (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - The Whale Ship Charles W. Morgan (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Photographs
  - New Bedford and Cape Cod (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - New Bedford - houses, circa 1890s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - New Bedford - buildings (exteriors and interiors) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - New Bedford - buildings (exteriors and interiors) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ships and harbor (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - On ship (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Texas trip: Marfa mines, Terlingua/Jaurez (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - China, Russia (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Eskimos" (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - William H. Shockley (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Walter A., William H., and George Shockley (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Grandma Rapp and Emmy" (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Unknown woman (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Framed photographs (various portraits) and watch (Box 4)
  - Album - William B. Shockley, Los Angeles area and mountain trip, circa 1930s (Box 5)
- Books/Notebooks
  - Russian Notes, by William H. Shockley (Box 3)
    Several bound articles, including, "Gold Dredging in the Urals, with Notes on Dredging in Siberia;" "The Bogoslovsk Mining Estate;" and "The People and Scenery of the Urals." Also includes handwritten notes.
  - The "Brownies" in "Yurep" or Cycling Beyond the Sea, by Charles R. Cutter and F. R. Goodrich. (Box 3)
  - In search of a Siberian Klondike, by Washington Baker Vanderlip and Homer Bezaleel Hulbert (Box 3)